I saw a headline this week that actually made me laugh out loud.
It was a serious tech article, but the premise, it just sounded like a setup for a bad sci-fi
movie.
Oh, yeah.
The author claimed they sat down and interviewed a piece of software.
It does sound a little ridiculous when you put it like that.
Right.
And I don't mean they interviewed the CEO or, you know, the lead engineer, not at all.
They claimed to have interviewed the code itself, specifically this new architecture behind
the Claude code.
They asked it, point blank, how do you actually work without messing everything up?
It's a bold approach, but the article we're digging into today by Zoltan Erdos is actually
quite brilliant.
It's called how Claude code engineers context and interview with Opus 4.6.
So we're taking this interview seriously then.
We have to because what Erdos uncovered isn't just about one tool.
It's really a masterclass in what he calls context engineering.
Okay.
It sounds impressive, but it also sounds a little like a buzz word invented to sell consulting
hours.
I get the skepticism I do.
We spent the last couple of years hearing all about prompt engineering, you know, finding
the magic spell to cast on the AI to get the right answer.
The magic words.
Exactly.
Context engineering is different.
It's not about the words.
It's about the architecture of the information itself.
Yeah.
It's about how you manage the AI's, well, it's limited working memory.
So it doesn't get confused or distracted or just plain stupid.
That's the part I really want to get into because I think most people, myself included,
assume computers don't get distracted.
They're machines.
They process data.
But this article suggests that if you feed an AI too much information, you're actually
hurting it.
You're not just hurting it.
You're effectively lowering its IQ.
And that's what we need to explore today.
The physics of why that happens and how this new plan mode feature in Claude code actually
fixes it.
Okay.
Let's start right there.
Plan mode.
The article describes this moment where you hit shift plus tab in the interface and the
whole AI just changes.
It stops trying to write code and starts to what contemplate.
Ideally, yeah.
To the user, it feels like the AI has shifted gears into a brainstorming mode.
Right.
But the interview reveals the mechanic is much simpler and honestly kind of funny.
The system isn't switching to a bigger smarter brain.
It's just slapping restriction on the model.
A restriction.
It's a constraint.
When you enter a plan mode, the system injects a hidden prompt that says essentially, you
are strictly prohibited from creating, modifying or deleting files.
So it's putting the AI in handcuffs.
Contextual handcuffs.
Yeah.
You could say that.
But think about why.
If the AI can write code, it will try to solve your problem immediately.
It'll just guess jumps the gun.
It does.
By removing its ability to act, the system forces the model to explore first.
It creates this space where the only thing the AI is allowed to do is read, search and
strategize.
That seems counterintuitive.
You make the AI smarter by taking away its tools.
You make it more deliberate.
And the output of this mode, the plan, it generates, that isn't just a to-do list for you.
This is the key insight.
The plan is a context engineered prompt for the next version of the AI that will actually
do the coding.
Explain that.
Why does the next version need a prompt?
Can't it just remember what it just thought about?
And this is the fundamental limitation of large language models that I think people
forget all the time.
Which is?
They have zero long-term memory.
None.
Every time you send a message, the AI is, for all intents and purposes, waking up for
the first time.
It has total amnesia.
It only knows what is currently in its context window.
It's like that movie, a memento.
That is the perfect analogy.
The AI is the guy with amnesia and the plan is the tattoo he writes on his arm so he
knows what to do when he wakes up five minutes later.
So the explorer AI looks around, figures out the problem, writes this plan.
Then the system wipes its memory, wakes up the coder AI, and just says, read this tattoo
and get to work.
That is exactly what happens.
And that tattoo the plan, it has to be incredibly specific.
If the explorer found a bug in, say, ASRC component center dot T-S-X, it needs to write that exact
file path in the plan.
Right.
If it doesn't?
The coder AI won't know that file even exists.
This brings us to the big question I had reading this.
The explorer goes out and reads files to build this plan.
Why do we even need this two step process?
Why can't I just upload my entire code base, all 10,000 files, and just say, fix the bug?
You could try.
Yeah.
But this is where we run into what the article calls the physics of attention.
Physics.
It's a hardware reality.
In these models, every single piece of text you feed it, the code, the comments, even
the white space is broken down into these things called tokens.
Right.
The model uses a mechanism called self attention to understand them.
Basically, every token has to look at every other token to figure out how they all relate.
OK.
So if I have a thousand words, every word is checking in with every other word.
Yes.
And here is the kicker that most people just don't realize.
Attention is a zero sum game.
Imagine the AI's attention is a pie, a single fixed size pie.
That pie represents 100% of the focus the model can give.
I like pie.
So if you feed the AI, say, a thousand tokens of relevant code, the stuff that actually
has the bug that code, get the nice big slice of the attention pie, the AI can see it
clearly.
Makes sense.
But if you then dump in 10,000 tokens of irrelevant documentation or random PDF files
or old chat while slicing the pie thinner, you're decimating the pie.
You're forcing the model to spread that same amount of attention over 10 times as much
data.
The signal of the actual bug gets completely diluted.
So it's not just that the extra info is clutter.
It literally makes the AI stupider regarding the specific task I gave it.
Stupider or at least much easier.
The article describes irrelevant context as toxic.
It actively degrades the signal.
That's why you get hallucinations.
The AI is trying to find a pattern in a sea of noise and just start seeing things that
aren't there.
That actually explains a lot.
I've had times where I've paced in a huge error log and the AI just seems to lose
its mind.
It's a grounding in noise.
And there's another layer to this physics problem.
It's not just about attention.
It's about the cost of reading versus writing.
The article mentioned a price difference, something like $5 for input versus $25 for
output.
Roughly that, yeah.
Input tokens, what the AI reads are cheap, output tokens, what it writes are expensive.
Why?
I would have thought reading a whole book takes more energy than writing a summary.
For a human, yes, for a GPU, it's the opposite.
When you feed a prompt to an AI, it processes all those words in parallel.
It's one giant mathematical operation, a matrix multiplication that happens all at once.
It's incredibly efficient.
Pre-fill.
That's the pre-fill phase.
But generating the answer, the decode phase, that is sequential.
The AI has to guess the first word.
Then it feeds that word back into itself to guess the second word.
Then the third, one by one.
So reading is like glancing at a photo, but writing is like painting a copy of that photo
by hand, pixel by pixel.
Perfect analogy.
And because writing ties up the hardware for so much longer, it costs way more.
This economic reality drives how these systems are architected.
It's why they want to use something called crompt caching.
I saw that term 92% prefix reuse rate.
That sounds like recycling.
It basically is.
If the beginning of your conversation, the system prompt, the list of tools, the project
rules.
If that stuff doesn't change, the AI doesn't have to reread it every single time.
It just remembers the math it did last time.
So it's like, if I ask you a question, you don't have to reread my biography to know who
I am.
You have that cast.
And because that cast memory is cheap, about 10% of the cost of reading new stuff, want
to keep the start of your prompt exactly the same.
You never put dynamic stuff at the top.
You append the new questions to the bottom.
So the structure is always static rules at the top, which are cheap and cash, and then
the new messy data at the bottom.
Exactly.
But there is a danger in just appending new data forever.
We circle right back to the attention pie.
If the chat gets too long, you run into context rot.
That sounds gross.
Is that like bit rot?
Worse.
It's when the AI starts believing its own lies.
Let's say early in the chat, the AI hallucinates a function called get user data v2.
It doesn't exist.
The AI just made it up.
Okay.
But now that hallucination is in the chat history.
It's in the context window.
Ten minutes later, you ask for a fix.
The AI looks back, sees get user data v2 in the history and thinks, ah, that must be
real.
It's right there in the transcript.
It gaslights itself.
It absolutely does.
It treats its own past output as absolute truth.
So how does cloud code handle this?
If I'm working on a huge project, the chat is going to get massive.
Am I just doomed to rot?
They use a strategy called compaction.
When the conversation history hits about 83% of the limit.
The system essentially takes a chainsaw to the middle of the conversation.
It just deletes it.
It summarizes it.
It throws away the blow by blow details of your previous errors and just keeps a high
level summary.
But, and this is the clever part, it re-injects the critical stuff, the tattoo, the plan file,
and the clawed.ed.md file, which holds your project rules are protected.
They get pasted back in after the purge.
So the AI loses the noise of the argument you just had, but keeps the instructions on
what to do next.
This feels like a very, very elaborate way to manage a very specific weakness.
It is.
And it highlights the biggest difference between human intelligence and AI intelligence.
Which is?
Metacognition.
Knowing what you don't know, if you ask me about quantum physics, I can stop and say,
I have no idea, let me go to the library.
But the AI just keeps talking.
The AI has no doubt mechanism.
If a fact is in its context window, even it's a hallucination, it treats it as reality.
It cannot step back and audit its own memory.
Which is why we still need humans.
For now, yeah.
The article argues, our role is shifting from code writer to assumption auditor.
We need to look at that plan and say, wait, why do you think that file exists?
We have to check the AI's work before it commits.
Okay, I want to pivot here.
We've geeked out on the internal mechanics, the handcuffs, the attention pie, the gas
lighting.
But a lot of our listeners aren't using clawed code.
They're using chat GPT or standard clawed or Gemini.
The interface might be different, but the brain works the same way.
So how do we apply this?
If I'm sitting in front of a standard chatbot, how do I context engineer my way to a better
answer?
You have to act like the architecture we just described.
You have to be the sub agent.
Be the intern.
So tactic number one, explore before you prompt.
Most people just paste an error message and screen help.
Guilty.
Don't do that.
You are polluting the context with panic.
Instead, find the files that are likely involved.
That's the content of those files first.
Prime the context window with the signal, then ask the question.
So do the manual labor of gathering the ingredients before you ask the AI to cook?
Precisely.
Tactic number two, reference.
Don't describe.
Humans are terrible at describing code.
We say things like, you know, that pattern we use in the other file with the hooks.
And the AI has no idea what you mean.
It's guessing.
Instead, just say, see scutlesauce.ts, follow that pattern.
The AI is an incredible mimic.
If you give it a concrete example in the context, it will copy the spacing, the naming conventions,
the error handling, everything.
It's much higher bandwidth than your English description.
Okay.
What about the context rot issue?
How do I manage that manually?
That's tactic three, the clean room.
If you have been arguing with the AI for 20 minutes and it's just going in circles, stop.
It's gaslighting itself again.
It is.
You cannot fix it by arguing more.
You're just adding more noise to the pie.
You need to ask the AI to summarize the current solution or plan, copy that text and open
a brand new chat window.
Reset the brain.
Total reboot.
Paste the plan into the fresh window.
You get zero dilution, zero history of errors, just the clean instruction that performance
differences night and day.
It takes a little more discipline though.
You have to recognize when you're in that doom loop.
You do.
But that's the job now.
We aren't prompt engineers anymore.
We are context architects.
You're managing the signal to noise ratio.
There is one last thing from the article that I have to bring up because it completely broke
my brain.
We've been talking about this interview with the software and the insights from Zoltan
Erdos.
But the outro of the article reveals something.
Well, meta.
The research method.
Yeah.
This wasn't just a guy reading code and writing an article.
He used the very method we just discussed to write the piece itself.
He used 16 parallel AI agents.
16, he had different agents reading the white papers, reading the documentation, reading
the source code, and they all distilled their findings and brought them back to a central
writer.
It's context engineering all the way down.
The article about context engineering was itself context engineered.
It's fascinating because it proves the point.
No single human and no single AI prompt could have held all that complexity and working
memory at once.
They had to break it down.
That's the takeaway.
Whether you are writing code, writing, and article, we're just trying to organize your
life.
Attention is a scarce resource to finite pie.
So stop filling it with junk.
Exactly.
Check your context hygiene.
Are you feeding the machine or your self-signal?
Or are you just drowning in noise?
Something to think about the next time you have 50 tabs open.
Thanks for listening to The Dupdive.
See you next time.